<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Important questions of state, law, justice and prudence both civil and religious, upon the late revolutions and present state of these nations / by Socrates Christianus.</title>
            <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61429</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5427</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R228417</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">20552666</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 20552666</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109452</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61429)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109452)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 515:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Important questions of state, law, justice and prudence both civil and religious, upon the late revolutions and present state of these nations / by Socrates Christianus.</title>
                  <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Revolution of 1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109452:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Important QUESTIONS Of State, Law, Juſtice and Prudence, Both Civil and Religious, UPON THE Late Revolutions AND PRESENT STATE OF THESE NATIONS.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Conſiſtere ſimul non poſſunt Voluntas Imperandi &amp; Voluntas Perdendi</p>
               <bibl>Grot. 1. de Juri Belle. c. 4. § 11.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Regi in partem non ſuam involanti vis juſta opponi poteſt: quia ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus Imperium non habet.</p>
               <bibl>Grot. ibm. § 13.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Quiſquis Imperii Summi partem habet, non poteſt non jus habere eam par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem tuendi. Quod ubi fit, poteſt Rex etiam ſuam Imperii partem Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li Jure amittere.</p>
               <bibl>Grot. ibm.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>Socrates Chriſtianus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:109452:2"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THe Deſign of this Paper is not what ſome might imagine by the Title, to raiſe Doubts and Queſtions, but the contrary, to prevent and reſolve them. Certain it is, that many Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are, and may be better, and with more Eaſe, Brevity, and Satisfaction, reſolved meerly by well ſtating the Queſtion, than by long Arguments and Diſcourſes. And the old Socratick way of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing and inſtructing by Queſtions, hath been thought by ſome Wiſe Men of latter Ages not leſs uſeful or ſatisfactory than that of Syllogiſtical Diſputations.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109452:2"/>
            <head>The preſent State of the Nation.</head>
            <p>WHERES <hi>King</hi> James <hi>the Second,</hi> being long ſince <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced</hi> from the Reformed Religion, wherein he was Educated, to the Superſtitions and Abominations of the Romiſh Religion, out of his great Zeal for the ſame, and through the Evil Counſels and Inſtigations of the Jeſuits, and of other Perſons of the ſame or the like wicked Principles and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, hath ever ſince with great earneſtneſs, and by various means <hi>endeavoured the Re-eſtabliſhment</hi> thereof, and the ſuppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and utter extirpation of the genuine Chriſtian Religion reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Superſtitions and Abominations of the <hi>Roman,</hi> and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly profeſſed under the protection of the Laws in theſe and divers other Nations, as of a Pernicious Hereſie, and under the Notion and Name of the <hi>Northern</hi> Hereſie. And for that end, <hi>during the Reign of the late King</hi> Charles <hi>the Second,</hi> held divers ſecret Counſels and Conſpiracies, both with notorious Enemies of the Reformed Religion beyond the Seas, and at home with Perſons notoriouſly guilty by the Laws of High Treaſon. And in purſuance of thoſe Counſels and Conspiracies, is generally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved to have been a Principal Author and Promoter of Wars, Bloodſhed, and other great Miſchiefs among the Profeſſors of the Reformed Religion; that being weakened by their own hands, they might the more eaſily be Deſtroyed and Subjugated by thoſe of his party.</p>
            <p>And whereas the ſaid King <hi>James, ſince his acceſs to the Throne,</hi> in further proſecution of the ſame Deſigns, Counſels, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies (not to mention any ſecret Practices, which may poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be made more manifeſt in due time) hath notoriouſly, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the true Conſtitution of the Government of this Nation, contrary to divers expreſs Statutes, contrary to his own repeated Word and Solemn Promiſes, and contrary to the very form of the uſual Coronation Oath (which he is preſumed to have taken)
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:109452:3"/>aſſumed to himſelf <hi>a Power to Suſpend and Diſpenſe with the Laws,</hi> (which is an Eſſential part of the Legiſlative Authority, which belongs not to the King alone) and under pretence thereof, keeping up a great <hi>Army in time of Peace,</hi> hath not only <hi>Armed great numbers of Papiſts,</hi> but put and continued in <hi>Offices,</hi> both <hi>in the Army and in the Navy,</hi> many Papiſts and others Perſons not qualified by Law.</p>
            <p>And that the <hi>Adminiſtration of Juſtice</hi> might be alſo in the hands of Papiſts, and ſuch as were believed would comply with his Deſigns, hath in <hi>the Counties</hi> choſen divers Papiſts for <hi>Sheriffs,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plac'd, and put out of Office moſt of the Proteſtant <hi>Juſtices of the Peace,</hi> and in their Room hath put and continued profeſſed Papiſts, and other Perſons not qualified by Law; inſomuch that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally throughout the Nation, in the <hi>Counties</hi> there is not a legal Juſtice of the Peace to be found in many miles diſtance, whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver occaſion ſhould happen: In <hi>Corporations</hi> hath by his Letters of <hi>Mandamus</hi> cauſed profeſſed Papiſts to be choſen for Mayors, Aldermen, and Sheriffs: And in the <hi>Courts of Juſtice at Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> hath placed and diſplaced <hi>Judges</hi> till he had furniſhed the ſame with ſuch as were believed would moſt perfectly comply with his Pleaſure, without much regard to the Laws.</p>
            <p>And for the promotion of thoſe Deſigns in <hi>the Church</hi> as well as <hi>State,</hi> hath granted to divers Perſons, of whoſe compliance therein he was well aſſured, a Commiſſion in the nature of the <hi>High Commiſſion</hi> (which with all other of like nature at any time to be granted, hath by expreſs Acts of Parliament been utterly aboliſhed and made void) by which he hath cauſed the preſent <hi>Lord Biſhop of London</hi> moſt unjuſtly and contrary to all Law and Equity to be Suſpended from his Office; the Preſident of <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and the <hi>Preſident and Fellows of</hi> Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen <hi>Colledge in</hi> Oxford, contrary to Law to be put out of their <hi>Free-holds;</hi> and by the ſame proceedings might (as may reaſonably be believed was deſigned) have turned out all the Clergy of <hi>England,</hi> who would not have complyed with what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he ſhould have pleaſed to command.</p>
            <p>And for the more <hi>direct reſtauration of the Papal Authority and Religion</hi> in <hi>England</hi> (which to endeavour or attempt is High Treaſon by the Statutes) hath ſent his <hi>Ambaſſador</hi> to the Biſhop <hi>of Rome,</hi> and admitted and entertained a Legate from him; hath permitted <hi>Popiſh Biſhops</hi> to be conſecrated in <hi>England,</hi> and to hold their Viſitations, a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> to be <hi>of his Privy Council, Jeſuit Schools,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:109452:3"/>and <hi>Convents for Fryers</hi> to be erected, and <hi>Popiſh Chapels</hi> for Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Maſs in divers places; and hath placed and permitted known Papiſts to hold conſiderable places and Employments in the Church and in the Univerſities.</p>
            <p>And that the things thus deſigned and promoted might have been confirmed with the <hi>Formalities of a legal Eſtabliſhment,</hi> hath uſed divers indirect Means, and imployed divers Agents, to have ſuch <hi>Perſons</hi> only <hi>choſen to ſerve in Parliament,</hi> as he could be aſſured would comply with his Pleaſure therein; a practice which ſtrikes at the very root of our Government, and tends directly as the moſt immediate means to the ſubverſion thereof.</p>
            <p>And to compleat all, that they might be ſo Eſtabliſhed and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured for the future from <hi>danger</hi> of being defeated by a <hi>Proteſtant Suceſſor,</hi> hath by the arts of thoſe Subtile Agents been ſo far tranſported in his Paſſion for that Painted Rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Religion, as to comply with them in an<note n="*" place="margin">Though it be in truth <hi>Unnatural,</hi> yet it may not ſeem ſo, or to be unreaſonable to one who reputes them to be obſtinate Hereticks; and for that Cauſe deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to be diſinherited.</note> unnatural intrigue to adopt or ſet up a <hi>Suppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titious Child</hi> (as is by moſt Perſons in the Nation of all Ranks and Qualities firmly believed, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Extrajudicial Depoſitions In-rolled and Publiſhed in Print) for his own Son and the Rightful Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> though to the diſinheriting of the true heireſs apparent and his own Children; that ſo he might have a pretended Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, to be Educated in the Popiſh Religion, and in time to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the Work he had begun; or (as is believed by ſome) to baffle all hopes of a Proteſtant Succeſſor for the preſent, and in due time to ſet up one of his Natural Sons of his own Religion.</p>
            <p>And whereas, when many <hi>Lords,</hi> both Spiritual and Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, <hi>Gentlemen</hi> and others of all Ranks; obſerving theſe things, and well conſidering the great and apparent Danger, that theſe Nations were by theſe means brought into, had, as the only <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy</hi> under God, craved aid of His Highneſs the <hi>Prince of</hi> Orange, (whoſe intereſt and concern in theſe matters, as well as Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to theſe Nations and to the Proteſtant Religion, did both qualifie and oblige him to interpoſe) and the Prince thereupon coming in with a Competent Army, had in a <hi>Declaration</hi> ſet out theſe and the like matters as the cauſe of his coming, and refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all to the Determination of a Free Parliament; the Nobility and Gentry and others dayly reſorting to him, and engaging in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109452:4"/>an Aſſociation with him for the Defence of the Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Antient Government, Laws, and Liberties of theſe Nations, and great parts of the Armly daily revolting to them; the ſaid King <hi>James</hi> was pleaſed at firſt ſo far to comply with theſe reaſonable Demands, as to order Writs for Elections to be Sealed, and yet not long after (whether through his Conſcience of the Illegality of his Actions, not able to endure the Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe matters, or through the inſtigations of his wicked Counſellours, or both) cauſed moſt of the ſaid Writs to be burnt, conveyed away the great Seal, the Pretended Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> the Queen, and divers of the Conſpirators in that Intrigue, and acceſſories thereunto; to prevent, as is believed, their croſs Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and further diſcovery of the whole Contrivance, and of the reſt of the Perſons concerned in it, and at laſt departed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf beyond the Seas, deſerting theſe Kingdoms and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof.</p>
            <p>All this being not only true, but notorious matter of Fact, ſo that the Relation of it needs neither Apology nor Proof; there ariſe thereupon ſeveral QUESTIONS, which may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the whole Nation and all Perſons therein, who have any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the due diſcharge of their Duty well to conſider, and in order thereunto.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> Queſtions of State, concerning the Conſtitution of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WHether by the <hi>Sacred Scriptures,</hi> or any <hi>Poſitive Law of God,</hi> there be any <hi>Particular Form of Government</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed for the ſeveral Nations of the World? or all be left at liberty to conſtitute any ſuch juſt form of Goverment, as to them ſhall ſeem moſt convenient? And all Perſons as ſtrictly obliged to the juſt and reaſonable Obſervance of thoſe Publick Pacts and Conſtitutions, whereby their ſeveral Governments are formed, as of any private Pacts whatſoever? and all again at full Liberty to uſe all juſt and reaſonable means for the preſervation thereof?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether by THE CONSTITUTION OF THE GO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VERNMENT OF <hi>ENGLAND</hi> in <hi>Legiſlation,</hi> or making of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109452:4"/>Laws the <hi>Jus Regiae Poteſtatis,</hi> or Regal Power, be more than one third part? of the Kings <hi>Negative Voice</hi> comprehend any thing more than what each of the Houſes have? And therefore his aſſuming as his Prerogative, of what belongs to the whole, be not an Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Rights, both of the Lords, and of the Commons; and within the ſixth Caſe of <hi>Hugo Grotius,</hi> 1. <hi>de Jure belli c.</hi> 4. § 13. wherein juſt force may be uſed againſt the Invador?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether by the Conſtitution of the Government of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> for the ordinary <hi>Adminiſtration of Juſtice,</hi> there be not <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Courts and Offices</hi> appointed, whoſe Authority the King can neither enlarge nor abridge; as in each County the Hundred Courts once in three Weeks, the County Court once in a Month, the Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> once in a Quarter or four times in a Year, the Circuits twice in the Year, and for Extraordinary Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, by the Common Law and Statutes yet in force and unrepealed, ths Parliament once in the Year at leaſt? So that the <hi>Regal Right</hi> in this reſpect extends little farther than firſt to the choice of the Perſons, and ſecondly, that the Commiſſion and all Proceſs be made in his Name, as the Supreme in the Government, and for the greater Honour and Majeſty of the King and Kingdom?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether by the Conſtitution of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, in all <hi>Ordinary matters between the King and the Subjects,</hi> the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Courts of Juſtice at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> have not Juriſdiction, and the Judges of theſe Courts be not the proper Legal Judges; who may and ought to judge and determine according to the Law of the Kings Right, and Actions, and of the Validity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and to order equal Right to be done to the Subjects, as well as to the King Himſelf?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Whether by the Conſtitution of the Government of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in all <hi>Extraordinary Matters, the High Court of Parliament</hi> be not the Supream Judicature; and may not of themſelves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the King both Judge and Correct the Errors and Miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the Judges and great Officers of the Nation, and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over enquire into the Actions of the King Himſelf, ſo far as they concern the Publick State of the Nation; and if they ſee cauſe, both judge and declare them to be publick Grievances and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Law, and alſo demand Redreſs by Petition, and alſo in caſes of great Importance and Neceſſity, when the Conſtitution and publick State of the Nation is in danger, by Force and Arms? And whether this Right doth not remain in the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109452:5"/>of this Nation in ſuch Caſe if the King refuſe to call a Parliament, there being then no Superiour Authority or other means to determine the matter between them, when the very damental Laws and Conſtitution are in Queſtion?</p>
               <p>Indeed it is plain in the Frame and Compoſure of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it ſelf and in the Actions of our moſt Antient and Succeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Parliaments, and confirmed by the Polititie of thoſe People from whom they did deſcend, that out Wiſe Anceſtors in the Conſtitution of this Government did particularly intend and take care of <hi>two things;</hi> The one to give all the <hi>Honour and Majeſty</hi> that could be to the King, for the greater Honour and Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to the Nation abroad: The other to retain all the <hi>Power</hi> that might be to themſelves, for the greater Security and Benefit of the Publick at Home. And therefore, when they had limited and confined his Power as much as was thought convenient, they inveſted him with the reſt, not as a <hi>Right</hi> which he might diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of, or uſe as he pleaſed, but as a <hi>Truſt,</hi> the management whereof they would inſpect and conſider; and for that end, as well as to inſpect the Actions of inferiour Officers, ſupply Defects, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> did think fit to have frequent Conventions or Parliaments. So that his <hi>Right</hi> hath a great and weighty <hi>Duty</hi> (if not a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in Law, as they call it) eſſentially annexed to it; and he is in effect only the Supream Officer, and a kind of <hi>High Reeve of the Nation,</hi> as the <hi>High Shire-reeve</hi> of the County, who in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reſpects doth truly repreſent him. And therefore becauſe ſome have in our Age aſſerted ſuch an <hi>Unaccountableneſs</hi> and <hi>Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtibility</hi> in the King as is inconſiſtent with this Conſtitution, and others from ſome Clauſes and Declarations preſcribed in ſome late <hi>Statutes paſſed ſoon after the Return of the late King</hi> Charles the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, may think themſelves bound in Conſcience to maintain the ſame, it may be neceſſary to propoſe to their ſerious conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſome few</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Queſtions concerning thoſe Clauſes, and the Oaths, and Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations preſcribed, in the Statutes of <hi>12, 13,</hi> &amp; <hi>14. Ch. 2.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. WHether they who did take theſe Oaths and declare ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, are thereby (being only <hi>Declarative</hi> of their belief at that time, and not <hi>promiſſary</hi> for the future) obliged to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109452:5"/>perſiſt in the ſame belief, and act accordingly in all caſes which may happen, without further Inquiring or Examination of the Truth of that matter?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether all or any of thoſe Clauſes, or the Oaths preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in the Statutes aforeſaid, being all meerly <hi>Declarative,</hi> and not <hi>Conſtitutive,</hi> do; or can make any real alteration in the Laws, and in the very Conſtitution of the Government from what they were before?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether <hi>the vulgar ſenſe</hi> of thoſe Clauſes, Oaths, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, be not <hi>inconſiſtant</hi> with the Natural and Original Right of Mankind, to defend and maintain their Rights? the ſpecial Conſtitution of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government? the frequent Practice of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliaments? and known Principles of Law allowed at this day? be not <hi>contrary</hi> to the Sentiments and Practices of moſt Nations of this part of the World? to the Judgment and Practice of divers Reformed Churches upon great deliberation in their own Caſe? and of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi>James, &amp;c.</hi> and the State of <hi>England</hi> in their Aſſiſtance to other People oppreſſed by their Kings and their Miniſters? and <hi>of dangerous Conſequences</hi> both to Prince and People? diſpoſing Princes with more Liberty to tranſgreſs the Laws, and expoſing innocent People, if they believe it to oppreſſion by them; if not, to Wars and Contention with them for the maintenance of their Right? and therefore the Clauſes and Declarations aforeſaid, to be either wholly rejected as falſe; or elſe accommodated with ſome better and more conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient ſenſe and Explication? as that, which no Man will deny, <hi>That neither the King, nor his Miniſters, acting according to Law, may be reſiſted upon any</hi> Pretence <hi>whatſoever.</hi> And it may deſerve ſome Conſiderations</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether conſidering the <hi>Time,</hi> when theſe Statutes were made, the ambiguous <hi>Terms</hi> in which the Declarations are drawn, neither reſtraining them to Lawful Actions and Commſſions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that would not ſerve the turn, nor expreſly extending to Unlawful, becauſe that was not likely to paſs; the <hi>Activity</hi> and cunning Inſinuation of the <hi>Romiſh Emiſſaries,</hi> and their real <hi>Intereſt</hi> to have the Government abſolute in one governable Prince, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than ſubject to the Counſels and Reſolves of an untractable Parliament, and the <hi>Tricks</hi> which they have ſince impoſed upon us; it be not likely that in theſe, as well as ſome other Statutes about and ſince that time, there may not be ſome of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109452:6"/>craftily intermixed, and unperceived in the tranſport the Nation was then in? and the rather if the late late King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, had before that time entred into their Communion, as is now believed?</p>
               <p>And becauſe in theſe things many well-meaning people may <hi>be impoſed upon,</hi> not only by the <hi>Authority of men,</hi> whoſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may be byaſſed by Proſpect of Favour and Advantage, but alſo by Ambiguity of words, as King, Abſolute, Imperial; it may be fit to note that the word <hi>King,</hi> doth not neceſſarily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port more than one having Supreme Executive power to govern according to Laws, as the King of <hi>England</hi> certainly hath, though the Parliament may judge whether he doth ſo or no. So that if any claim more, that is to be prov'd from the ſpecial Conſtitution of the Government. So the word <hi>Abſolute,</hi> when that is attributed to the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> it is to be underſtood not in reſpect of Laws, but of Tenure. They hold not of Pope, Emperor, or any other perſon or State. And in like manner the word <hi>Imperial,</hi> when uſed of the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> it imports no more than that it is not held of any other Crown.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Queſtion of Law, Juſtice and Prudence, upon the Matter of Fact before related.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WHether the Matter of Fact before related, doth not contain divers very high, <hi>deliberate, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved Violations of the Laws,</hi> and Conſtitution, and tending di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly and manifeſtly to the <hi>Subverſion of the true and ancient Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> of this Nation, and be not good Evidence, and a plain Declaration, that the ſaid King <hi>James</hi> did certainly deſign and endeavour the Subverſion thereof, and to make it Arbitrary; and was therefore an <hi>Enemy to it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether all this being done at the inſtigation of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and in favour of their Religion, (which obligeth them all, both Prince and People, to uſe their utmoſt endeavour for the <hi>Extirpation of Hereticks,</hi>) be not alſo good Evidence and an open Declaration, (notwithſtanding their pretence of Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,) that he was alſo an Enemy to the Religion and People of this Nation, being Proteſtants, and by the Pope and his party reputed and condemned for Hereticks?</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:109452:6"/>
               <p n="3">3. Whether the ſaid King <hi>James,</hi> having aſſumed to himſelf a power of Suſpending and diſpenſing with the Laws, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>invaded the Rights of the Lords and Commons,</hi> and thereby, and by many other open Acts declared himſelf <hi>an Enemy</hi> to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, Religion and people of this Nation, (which are things inconſiſtent with the Ends and Being of Government and Civil So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety,) and all this contrary to his Solemn Coronation Oath, and through the perſwaſion and inſtigation of Jeſuits and others, notoriouſly guilty by the Laws of High Treaſon, hath not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by demonſtrated himſelf incapable of the Government of this Nation, and not to be further intruſted therewith? and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether <hi>the Prince of Orange his Coming in</hi> to preſerve and maintain the Right of the Princeſs and himſelf, and to defend and protect an Innocent people in the Legal enjoyment of their Religion, Rights, and Liberties, from Violence, Oppreſſion and Deſtruction, deſigned and prepared (as is believed) againſt them contrary to the Laws, as Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and the people of this Nation had heretofore done for his Anceſtors and Countrey, be not juſtifiable by the Laws of God and man?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Whether <hi>the Lords, Gentlemen, and others</hi> of this Nation, who in this caſe, for the preſervation of themſelves and their Country, invited the Prince to come in, or after his coming en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Aſſociation with him, for the Ends aforeſaid, did any thing therein but what was neceſſary, juſt, and lawful by the Laws of God and Man, the Conſtitution of this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and many precedents in this Kingdom?</p>
               <p n="6">6. Whether the <hi>Officers and Souldiers,</hi> who had indefinitely entred into the Service of the King, are not to be preſumed to have acted therein as rational men, and to have intended a reaſonable and legal Service to their King and Country, for the preſervation of the legal Government, Laws and Liberties thereof, and not a ſlaviſh Service to the will of a Tyrant, and Enemy of their Country; and therefore in deſerting the King, and revolting to the Prince and his Aſſociates, when this came to be diſputed, did not do an act of greater Generoſity, Loyalty, end Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to the Government and their Country, than if they had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in his Service, and brutiſhly, or upon a vain and miſtaken principle of Honour, aſſiſted to the ſubverſion of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the deſtruction of their Country-men, and the ſuppreſſion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109452:7"/>and extirpation of the Religion, which they themſelves do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs?</p>
               <p>The common abuſe of the term <hi>Loyalty,</hi> to impoſe upon the Nation, makes it neceſſary to explain <hi>the genuine Notion</hi> of it. Which is nothing elſe, when attributed to Perſons, but either the ſtate of a Free-man, or <hi>Jus civitatis,</hi> or a conformity of the Will and Actions to the Laws of the Land, and the Government by Law Eſtabliſhed. But that <hi>vulgar notion</hi> of Loyalty, whereby many well meaning Men have by the Sophiſtry of Jeſuits and ill deſigning Diſloyal Men, been impoſed upon, taken for an Active Compliance with, or at leaſt paſſive Submiſſion to the Will and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Prince, whether conformable to the Laws and Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Government, or not, is in theſe deſigning men plainly Kna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, Sycophantry, and Treachery, againſt both King and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and hath betrayed a whole race of Kings into great Miſchiefs and Deſtructions.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Whether upon due conſideration of the precedent Queſtions, <hi>all the reſt</hi> of the Proteſtants of theſe Nations ought not <hi>in Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, Juſtice and Charity</hi> to their Country, <hi>to unite</hi> and join with the ſaid Lords, Gentlemen, and others, who have aſſociated for the end aforeſaid, and unanimouſly agree <hi>to commit the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> Crown and Dignity thereof to the next undoubted Heir of the Royal Family, who is duly qualified for the ſame? or, by mutual agreement of all parties to ſuch of the Royal Family as is beſt qualified for the Management thereof in the preſent Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances? leſt otherwiſe by their unneceſſary over-cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſcrupulous forbearance they give occaſion and incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to diſcontented Perſons to involve all in ſuch new Troubles, Factions, Inſurrections, and Diſturbance of the Publick Peace and Settlement, as by their more generous Unanimity might eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be prevented?</p>
               <p>And becauſe here may ariſe ſome <hi>Scruples from the Oaths</hi> of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance and Supremacy, theſe things as to that may be conſidered.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whether the Duty of the Subject be not proportionable to the Right of the King, and extends no further?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether, the word <hi>Heirs</hi> ought not to be intended, firſt, of legal and undoubted Heirs? ſecondly, of ſuch as are duly qualified for the Diſcharge of ſuch a Publick Truſt and Office, and not of any ſuch as are <hi>non compos mentis,</hi> or, which is worſe, do <hi>cum ratione inſanire,</hi> and would confound and deſtroy all?</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:109452:7"/>
               <p n="3">3. Whether in the caſe of Succeſſion, both the Practice of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Times, and an Antient Formality uſed at the Coronation, be not Evidence of a Right of judging and choice upon a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al occaſion, of a fit Perſon of the Royal Family to ſucceed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in the Lords and Commons of this Nation?</p>
               <p n="8">8. Whether theſe Nations profeſſing themſelves <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ought not <hi>in Duty to God, and Prudence to themſelves,</hi> to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge with all Reverence and Devotion, his Admirable, Wiſe, Powerful, and Gracious <hi>Providence,</hi> in theſe late extraordinary Revolutions, and great and ſeaſonable Deliverance from ſo many and great, both incumbent Evils, and impendent Dangers over them? and to expreſs their ſenſe thereof, both by Solemn Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings, by a ſpeedy and effectual Reformation of that Torrent of Debauchery introduced and deſigned for their Ruine, and by all dutiful Concurrence with the Indications of his Will thereby intimated to us?</p>
               <p n="9">9. Whether it be not reaſonable for a Chriſtian Nation to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, That the ſaid <hi>King James</hi> having Unhappily by the delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Papiſts <hi>deſerted the true Religion,</hi> wherein he was Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, and revolted to the Superſtitions and falſe Religion which they profeſs, may not by the ſpecial Providence and Righteous Judgment of God for the ſame, and other ſins, be deſerted and <hi>left to the Deluſion alſo</hi> of their unſound and deceitful Policies, and thereupon to be <hi>deſerted by his People, and the Army</hi> in which he truſted, as was <hi>Rehoboam</hi> by the ten Tribes?</p>
               <p n="10">10. Whether <hi>the Special Providence of God,</hi> ſo viſible and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in this caſe, may not juſtly be looked upon by all ſerious Proteſtants, as <hi>a Manuduction</hi> and Indication of his Will, that theſe Nations ſhould concur therewith, in a cauſe ſo juſt and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>to the Excluſion of the ſaid King James</hi> from the Government there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and to commit the ſame to ſome other more proper Perſon of the Royal Family? and whether all, <hi>who ſhall obſtinately refuſe to concur</hi> therein, have not ſome reaſon to fear that they may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in ſome degree partake of the ſame Divine Judgments?</p>
               <p n="11">11. Whether it be not alſo a Chriſtian Duty incumbent upon theſe Nations; upon this occaſion to take into their ſerious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration all thoſe <hi>other Actions of the King,</hi> (beſides his revolt to the Romiſh Superſtitions and Abuſes) which may reaſonably be believed to have <hi>contributed,</hi> as well through the Judgments of God, as by their natural Efficacy, to the bringing of all this Evil
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109452:8"/>upon him; and thereupon ſpeedily to make all ſuch effectual Proviſion, as may be neceſſary for the prevention or removal of the ſame and the like occaſions of miſchief from the Nation it ſelf?</p>
               <p n="12">12. And whether among ſuch actions may not juſtly be reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned as Notorious, firſt, Uncharitable fomenting and promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Diſſentions and Diſtractions between Chriſtian Nations and People. Secondly, Diſcountenancing the ſerious profeſſion and practice of the Reform'd Religion, and Irreligious encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging <hi>Profaneneſs and Debauchery,</hi> both by Example, and by Impunity and Connivance. Thirdly, Unjuſt <hi>Violation of the Laws and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Government</hi> (contrary to the Coronation Oath) and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to make it arbitrary, by various illegal Practices both upon the <hi>ordinary Courts of Juſtice,</hi> by making the Judges Patents to be only <hi>durante bene placito;</hi> and then diſplacing ſuch as would not, contrary to their Conſcience and Duty, comply with his pleaſure and Deſigns; and upon <hi>the High Court of Parliament</hi> it ſelf, by perverting and interrupting the Legal Freedom of Elections, both in the Corporations, and in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and tampering with the Members themſelves, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For which and the like Evils, ſpeedy, proper, and effectual Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ought to be provided.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:109452:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Queſtions of Prudence, Religion, and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation,</hi> upon the late Revolutions and preſent State of the KING.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> WHether the King, having by ſad Experience found the ſo much admired <hi>Knowledg and Subtilty of the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits</hi> eſpecially, <hi>and other Emiſſaries</hi> of the Church of Rome, ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niciouſly erroneous and deceitful <hi>in matters of Policy,</hi> hath not juſt cauſe to ſuſpect that it may be ſo alſo <hi>in matters of Religion,</hi> and thereupon, now at his Leiſure, to retire into ſome convenient place of Freedom, and there to take a farther and impartial Examination, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be not ſo indeed?</p>
            <p>This may poſſibly be done effectually by well weighing but of <hi>two Conſiderations,</hi> of <hi>great Importance,</hi> and yet of <hi>no great Intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy;</hi> the one concerning <hi>the Head of their Church,</hi> the other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>the Body of their Religion,</hi> and the nature and Tendency of it, compared with the nature and Tendency of the Genuine Chriſtian Religion. Firſt, <hi>Whether all that ſpecial Authority and Power, which the Biſhops of</hi> Rome <hi>have ſo long claimed and exerciſed as peculiar to themſelves, and derived from Chriſt by St.</hi> Peter, <hi>be not a groſs Impoſture?</hi> As it needs muſt be, if either <hi>no ſpecial Authority</hi> was ever either <hi>given or promiſed</hi> by Chriſt to St. Peter, or <hi>exerciſed or claimed</hi> by him, more than what was given by Chriſt to all his Apoſtles, <hi>John 20.19, 23. Mark 16.15.</hi> or exerciſed by them; or no ſpecial Authority was ever <hi>conveyed</hi> by St. Peter to the Church or Biſhops of Rome, more than to any other Church or Biſhop which he Founded and Inſtituted. And beſides their <hi>defect of Proof,</hi> (which lyeth upon them to make out) in the one from the Scripture, and in the other from good Authority; there are two things of great weight againſt them. <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the ancient Biſhops of Rome claimed no ſpecial Authority peculiar to themſelves, but by <hi>other and inferiour Title,</hi> and what was <hi>much leſs</hi> than they now claim. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That there was very groſs <hi>Impoſture and Forgery</hi> uſed for the intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing and promoting of this pretended Authority. And if this Pillar of their Church fall, the other, their pretended <hi>Infallibility,</hi> muſt by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109452:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>conſequence fall with it. And of this Subject may be Read, <hi>Dr. Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> of the Supremacy, with <hi>Dr. Cave</hi> of the ancient Government of the Church. <hi>Secondly, Whether all that which is properly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> Popery <hi>be not ſuch another Corruption of</hi> the genuine Chriſtian Religion, <hi>by humane inventions influenced by the ſubtilty of Satan, as was that of the Law of</hi> Moſes <hi>by the Scribes and Phariſees at the time of the coming of our Saviour? and directly tending to oppoſe, enervate and affront the ſame?</hi> This may eaſily be percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by comparing the eſſential parts of the Christian Religion with the oppoſite Corruptions of Popery, and the Tendency of each. As <hi>1.</hi> The Example of the Heads, Chriſt and his Apoſtles with that of the Pope and his Cardinals. <hi>2.</hi> The Doctrine. <hi>3.</hi> The Worſhip. <hi>4.</hi> The Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline. <hi>5.</hi> The Means of Propagation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And to this purpoſe may be read <hi>Dr. Moor</hi>'s <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> and a little Tract call'd <hi>the Myſtery of Iniquity Unvailed,</hi> Written by Mr. <hi>Allen,</hi> but Printed without his Name.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2. Whether, if upon ſuch farther Examination, it ſhould pleaſe God to open his Eyes, and give him a clear ſight of his Errors, and of the Evils he hath committed, as well as thoſe he hath brought upon himſelf; it will not be</hi> his Duty and his Wiſdom <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately thereupon to apply himſelf to do the part of a true Penitent indeed? to humble himſelf, give Glory to God, by Confeſſing and Lamenting his Sins, acknowledging the Juſtice of his Judgments, and accepting his Puniſhment, be content with a retired penitent Life; and thereby as a part of Reſtitution en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the Peace of theſe Nations, which he hath ſo much diſturbed, not giving any farther diſturbance himſelf, or encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging any diſcontented erſon, but abandoning all Colour and pretence for any ſuch Matter?</hi> This would certainly prove <hi>his direct way to Happineſs</hi> hereafter, and poſſibly to greater Happineſs even here than he could ever have enjoyed amidst the Diſtractions of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of three Kingdoms. And all real Happineſs I heartily wiſh him both here and hereafter.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3. Whether it may not be fit, notwithſtanding he may not be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther truſted with the Government of theſe Nations, upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of Humanity,</hi> to treat him <hi>with Pity, Civility, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and a Competent Annual</hi> Allowance; <hi>yet ſuch as may not by good Husbandry become in time a means of New Diſturbance, and upon Condition that he do peaceably retire to ſome remote parts, as</hi> Italy, <hi>or the like, and continue there, or at that diſtance without further trouble to theſe Nations or himſelf?</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
